<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-11-22T17:59:46+00:00</updated><id>https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to do well in Part II Dissertation</title><link href="https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/blog/2022/part-ii-dissertation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to do well in Part II Dissertation"/><published>2022-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/blog/2022/part-ii-dissertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/blog/2022/part-ii-dissertation/"><![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: What I’ve written here is solely based on my own experiences. I hesitated in posting it as there is no right way of doing your dissertation. However, I still remembered how clueless I was when I first started it, so I hope some may find these beneficial. I also suggest reading <a href="https://mukulrathi.com/tripos/part-ii-compsci-dissertation-advice/">Mukul’s post</a>, while mine is more supplementary in nature.</p> <p><strong>Choosing the project and supervisor:</strong></p> <p>If you know exactly what you want to work on, that’s great! If not, and you’re unsure about your interests based on past Part IA/IB courses, that’s absolutely fine! I suggest:</p> <ul> <li>Start by looking at different research groups at CL, which offers a list of possible themes to narrow down. Past dissertation list is also a good starting point.</li> <li>Look at faculty members’ websites, which often summarise their specific research topics.</li> <li>Read their recent publications to see if the topic really interests you.</li> <li>Reach out for further discussion. <ul> <li>Don’t be deterred if you don’t yet have a clear idea. Think more about whether the general topic interests you. Project ideas usually come after several initial discussions. Supervisors will often suggest more specific directions for you to choose from.</li> <li>Most faculty members list potential Part II ideas on their websites, but don’t feel constrained by this list. You can always propose ideas outside the list to see if they also agree. They may also introduce you to their PhD students who will supervise you more closely.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>It is an important skill to search for supervisors that match your interests. I understand that the decision-making process can be stressful due to the uncertainty it contains, but my advice is to really prioritise your interest to be the most important criterion. You will spend an entire year working independently on this project.</p> <p><strong>Prior to Part II:</strong></p> <p>You must state your ‘‘Starting Point’’ very clearly in your dissertation, so anything (e.g., code) you do before Michaelmas term will not count. However, it would be helpful to read up on background materials during the summer prior to the actual execution. This can include theories outside the syllabus or the use of essential libraries. You should also take some time to discuss the project proposal with your supervisor during this period. I believe these two steps will prepare you to be confident enough when starting the new academic year.</p> <p><strong>Executing the project:</strong></p> <p>Each project differs in nature, but below are some things that I find generic enough for most projects:</p> <ul> <li>Keep a (weekly) log book: This advice was given by my supervisor, which I found extremely helpful and essential. You can summarise your weekly progress, experiment results, and questions, which can serve as discussion points at weekly meetings. Most importantly, it allows you to trace back everything when writing the dissertation and to spot the storyline of your project.</li> <li>Follow the timeline: It is critical to come up with a reasonable timeline in your proposal and to adhere to it strictly (hopefully). I aimed to complete the Success Criteria by the end of the winter holiday and work on Extensions during Lent term. This provides ample buffer time for unpredictable circumstances and sufficient exploration time. But each project is different, so consult your supervisor!</li> <li>Communication: Ensure your supervisor is well-informed of your progress. Communication solves many problems, so don’t hesitate to approach them! It is also extremely helpful to keep your DoS updated with your progress so that they can also give advice on the overall execution.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Writing the dissertation:</strong></p> <p>The dissertation is the only component marked by the examiners. I personally think the dissertation has so much weight that it can entirely transform your project depending on its presentation. However, I have only done it once (update: now twice after Part III - which I decided to adopt a totally different approach), so, speaking from my personal experience, which may not be optimal, I found the following helpful:</p> <ul> <li>Write throughout the year: <ul> <li>I came across this advice quite late in the year, so I only started to jot down point forms in my dissertation skeleton from Lent term onwards. Leaving point forms or even random ideas is quick and requires less thinking. When you start the actual writing of 10,000 words, you aren’t starting with a blank page, which reduces mental stress. You can also freely restructure your dissertation by rearranging the point forms, allowing you to better track what has been done and what is lacking.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Start early: <ul> <li>This varies among individuals and the progress of their project. Some prefer to start writing earlier. However, I cannot multitask, and I had to get into the flow for writing. What I did was spend the first two weeks of the Easter holiday writing my dissertation exclusively. I completed the core sections (Preparation, Implementation, Evaluation) by the end of it. This left me with the rest of the holiday for getting feedback, refining my dissertation, and, most importantly, revising for exams.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Draft many versions: <ul> <li>Don’t be afraid to change what you have written. The first draft is rarely optimal, and the next version can only be better. For me, I roughly had four versions: (i) the point forms that I wrote prior to the actual writing; (ii) the detailed account of everything I knew and did; (iii) the reduced version to meet the word limit; (iv) the final version that ties everything together.</li> <li>Word limit: Everyone complains about the word and page limit. I had to cut down several thousand words, which felt impossible at the time. But it was a great opportunity to discard unnecessary details and focus on the truly essential achievements to impress the examiners.</li> <li>The introduction is the trickiest part for me. I spent more time on the introduction than any other part and drafted many completely different versions. Whether to write it last, as I did, is up to you, but it’s crucial as it sets the overall tone for the dissertation. The reader should get a clear overall picture of what you are doing and why it is important.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Get feedback: <ul> <li>You don’t need to complete a full draft before seeking feedback from your supervisor/DoS. It is more efficient to get immediate feedback frequently once you complete a significant chunk. However, you should maintain the overall flow if you are sending in pieces. You may also want to seek feedback earlier to avoid the period when everyone is submitting their dissertations.</li> <li>It helps to involve others: I am extremely grateful to all my friends who helped proofread my dissertation and provided valuable feedback. It is essential that a Part IB student can understand your dissertation, so find someone! I even asked my NatSci/Eng friends to read it to see if it made sense to them.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Things to keep in mind: <ul> <li>Ensure it is easy to read.</li> <li>Ensure it tells a story.</li> <li>Ensure it is understandable.</li> <li>Highlight your contribution.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p><strong>Viva:</strong></p> <ul> <li>If you are called for a viva, usually there may be a reason. It is important (no joke) but still quite casual. You can prepare some slides (max 6 pages) to guide your viva presentation. They should highlight the key points of your project and contributions. You don’t need to worry too much about it if you have done everything yourself and were honest in your dissertation.</li> <li>One thing I wish I had known is that the examiners present at the viva might not have all read your dissertation. So, don’t assume they know what your project is about.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Post-dissertation: How to respond to the marks?</strong></p> <p>After a year of dedication, the dissertation is definitely very special to you! I found my Part II project to be the absolute highlight of my undergraduate years, even before receiving the marks. I am forever grateful to my supervisors and everyone I got to know because of this project. I want to say that even though our dissertations are labeled with some marks, these numbers do not reflect the actual experience and achievement. This is different from exams, and there is much stochasticity involved! What really matters is how you personally feel about your project and, most importantly, what you take away from it. Don’t let external evaluation metrics affect your own judgment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with bibliography]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dransyhe.github.io/dransyhe/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>